Guide to the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490 Records WAG.042
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490 Records
1884-1970s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Local 490
WAG.042
12 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes and 11 oversize flat boxes.
The International Brotherhood of Painters, Local 490 (more commonly known as the Paperhangers Local), were established in 1864, located in New York City. The union was most active in the first half of the 20th century. The collection is made up of ledgers, minute books, financial records, and other related materials.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Robert Eckersdorff, president of the local union, in 1986. The accession numbers associated with this gift are 1986.039 and 1986.040.
Historical/Biographical Note
The International Brotherhood of Painters, Local 490 (more commonly known as the Paperhangers), were established as a single exclusive local since 1864, located in New York City. The were originally known as section 70: Paperhangers Local Union of America and joined the Knights of Labor in 1886. In 1902, they joined the National Brotherhood of Painters, Decorators, and Paperhangers of America as Local 585. For a short time, the local preferred to affiliate with the independent Amalgamated Society of Painters (1904-1906). Since 1906, the paperhangers have been organized as Local 490 of District Council 9 of the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. During the 19th century, membership included a large number of German and English. In 1903, a large influx of Jewish paperhangers joined the union; total membership was between 60 and 120 men. As of 1980, membership was roughly 40 percent Jewish, with a strong presence of Italian and Puerto Rican members. As of 1984, there were about 300 members.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series:
Series I: Records
Series II: Photographs
Materials are alphabetically in each series.
Related Archival Materials
Carl Blum Papers (WAG 100)
Daniel French (WAG 101)
Sam Winn Papers (WAG 203)
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of the International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades, Local 490, also known as the Paperhangers union, from the late 1800s to first half of the 20th century in New York City. The collection is made up of membership ledgers, financial records, minute books, by-laws, photographs, correspondence, convention materials, and other ephemera. The collection is rich in demonstrating the demographics of the union from the early 20th century, as well as information and the paperhangers industry.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials in boxes 3-13 are extremely fragile. Materials must be looked at using a book cradle.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Ledgers (account books).; Painters, Industrial -- Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Painters, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Minute books.; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Painters District Council 9 of New York City; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades. Local 490
- Series I: Records, 1905-1962
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains the records of the Paperhangers union. The majority of this series is made up of ledgers, minute books, and financial records of the union, dating from 1800s to the middle of the century. Other types of material in the series include materials related to their Annual Eastern Seaboard Conference, flyers, correspondence, election materials, membership materials, and other ephemera. The series documents not only the day to day maintenance of the union, but also documents the union's support of other causes, including raising money for the State of Israel, and protesting in solidarity with other unions.
  - Application for Membership, 1906, 1930-1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - By-Laws and Amendments, 1916-1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence to Local 490, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence to Local 490, 1910-1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Election Documents, undated, 1933-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Envelopes, 1904-1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Board Correspondence, undated, 1910-1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Executive Board Trial Information, 1905-1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Executive Board Trial Information, 1949-1951 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Executive Board Trial Information, 1952-1957 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial Records of Paperhangers Local Union 490, 1906-1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Financial Reports, 1927-1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Flyers, Notices, and Invitations, 1930-1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Membership Information, 1937-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Documents, 1910-1962 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1940s-1952 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Monthly Report of Financial Secretary, Jan-Dec 1916 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Monthly Report of Financial Secretary, Jan-Dec 1917 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Monthly Report of Financial Secretary, Jan 1918 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Paperhangers Union Local 490 Awards, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Postage Receipts, 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 1930-1956 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Registration Cards for the Fourth Paperhangers Eastern Seaboard Conference, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - State of Israel Dollar Bonds and Raffle Tickets, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Trade Union Committee for the Support of Westinghouse Strikers: Contribution List Local 490, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minute Book and Ledgers, 1884-1909 (Box 3)
  - Record Books, 1901, 1904, 1908 (Box 4)
  - Minute Books, 1913, 1915 (Box 5)
  - Ledger, 1932-1933 (Box 6)
  - Record Books, 1932, 1937 (Box 7)
  - Record Books, 1941-1944 (Box 8)
  - Ledgers, 1906-1936 (Box 9)
  - Minute Books, 1916, 1925, 1929 (Box 10)
  - Ledger, 1934-1935 (Box 11)
  - Minute Book and Bookkeeping, 1903-1904 (Box 12)
  - Bookkeeping and Addresses, 1921 (Box 13)
- Series II: Photographs, 1937-1970s
  This series contains mostly black-and-white photographs, with some color photographs and negatives, depicting the Paperhangers union. Many deal with their annual Eastern Seaboard Conference. A portion of the black-and-white photographs were originally bound by a photo album. The photo album was photocopied and disassembled for preservation purposes. Other photographs depict portraits and other images of union members and protest photographs.
  - 2nd Annual Paper Hangers Eastern Seaboard Conference, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - 2nd Annual Paper Hangers Eastern Seaboard Conference: Photo Album [1 of 2], 1958 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - 2nd Annual Paper Hangers Eastern Seaboard Conference: Photo Album [2 of 2], 1958 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 3rd Annual Paper Hangers Eastern seaboard Conference and Wall Covering Exhibit, Jun 1959 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - 4th Annual Paper Hangers Eastern Seaboard Conference and Wall Covering Exhibit, 1960 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - 5th Annual Paper Hangers Eastern Seaboard Conference and Wall Covering Exhibit: Negatives, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - 5th Annual Paper Hangers Eastern Seaboard Conference and Wall Covering Exhibit: Photographs, 1961 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - 53rd Anniversary Affair, 1958 (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Annual Paper Hangers Eastern Seaboard conference and Wall Covering Exhibit, undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Brennan, Peter; French, Danny; and DiSilvestro, Mike, 1970s (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - J.I.B. Protest Photo, undated (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, Oct 1958 (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, Nov 1959 (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous, Dec 1960 (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - Office Photos (Sam Winn), undated (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Paper Hangers Work Shop, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Raftery, Frank S.: Portrait, undated (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Weinstock, Louis: May Day Parade, Negative, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Weinstock, Louis: May Day Parade, Photo, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Weinstock, Louis: On a Boat with Others, undated (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - Wolford, James: Portrait, undated (Box 14, Folder 22)